Dorothea A. Dreier
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Dorothea A. Dreier papers
1881-1941, bulk 1887-1923
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Dreier, Dorothea A.
2.6 linear feet
The papers of artist and art patron Dorothea A. Dreier measure 2.6 linear feet and date from 1881-1941, with the bulk of the material dating from 1887-1923. The papers document the life and work of Dorothea Dreier and also contain the papers of and about members of her immediate family, particularly her sisters, Mary and Katherine Dreier, and Margaret Dreier Robins. Found are correspondence, printed materials, legal and financial records, photographs, and one sketchbook by Dreier.
Provenance
The bulk of the collection was donated to the Archives of American Art in 1959 by Mrs. Peter Voorhees, Dorothea A. Dreier's neice. Additional materials were donated in 2007 by Theodore and Barbara Dreier, Dreier's great-nephew and great-neice.
Related Material
The papers of Katherine S. Dreier related to the Société Anonyme Archives are located at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Yale University.
The Schlesinger Library at the Radcliffe Institute of Harvard University holds the papers of Mary E. Dreier
Alternative Forms Available
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2008 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website. Duplicate materials, banking records and a portion of the printed materials were not scanned.
Restrictions on Access
The bulk of this collection has been digitized and is available online via the Archives of American Art's website.
Biographical Note
Dorothea A. Dreier was born on December 8, 1870, in Brooklyn, New York to German immigrant parents. The second of five children in a close knit, socially progressive family, her siblings include the social reformers and suffragettes Mary E. Dreier and Margaret Dreier Robins. However she was closest to her youngest sister, Katherine S. Dreier, fellow artist, patron of modern art and cofounder of the Société Anonyme, an organization dedicated to the promotion of modern art in the United States. Her sole brother, H. Edward Dreier, followed his father into business and managed the family investments.
Of all the Dreier sisters, Dorothea is the least well-known and there is scant information about her artistic career. It appears that she began her formal art training with John Twachtman and William Merritt Chase, although accounts disagree as to whether it took place at the Art Students League or the National Academy of Design. In 1904 Dorothea and her sister Katherine began studying with the painter Walter Shirlaw, with whom they developed a close friendship. Both sisters also traveled abroad frequently as the family maintained close ties with their German relatives and they combined these visits with trips to museums and galleries throughout Europe where they studied the works of the Old Masters as well as more contemporary artists. As evidenced by her series of oil paintings of Dutch weavers of 1908, Dorothea was greatly influenced by Van Gogh's early paintings of rural Dutch peasant life and she spent long periods abroad living and painting in Laren, The Netherlands. Her later paintings depicted landscapes, both in The Netherlands and the Adirondacks, as well as a series of New York street scenes.
Unfortunately, during a 1913 sojourn in Laren, Dorothea contracted tuberculosis. She remained at Saranac Lake, a renowned treatment center in the Adirondacks from late December 1913 to sometime in 1916. During her convalescence, Dorothea remained actively involved in the arts as she continued to paint and draw and supported her sister Katherine's work at the Cooperative Mural Workshop, a short-lived combination art school and workshop that focused on the decorative arts.
In 1920, Dorothea supported Katherine's decision to champion modern art and made generous financial contributions toward the establishment of the Société Anonyme, where Dorothea's first solo exhibition took place in 1921. This was her only solo exhibition prior to her untimely death in 1923. In the spring of 1925, Christian Brinton of the Brooklyn Museum of Art organized a memorial exhibition for which Katherine Dreier privately published a limited edition catalogue.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the painter Dorothea A. Dreier measure 2.6 linear feet and date from 1881 to 1941, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1887-1923. These papers document not only her life and work as an artist, but also the activities of her distinguished family in the realms of social reform, women's suffrage, and politics, through correspondence, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, broadsides, exhibition catalogs, publications, photographs, ephemera, a sketchbook, and legal and financial records.
Biographical materials include official documents, childhood writings, notes, ephemera, membership cards, invitations, programs, notes, lists, and legal and financial records.
Measuring 1.2 linear feet, correspondence is the largest and most extensive series and consists of letters from family and close friends as well as business correspondence. Although the letters in this series span from 1881-1925, a large number stem from Dorothea's 1913-1916 stay at Saranac Lake for treatment of her tuberculosis.
Family correspondents consist of members of Dorothea's immediate family as well as more distant relations, including those who resided in her parent's native Germany. Letters from her sisters Mary E. Dreier, and Margaret (Gretchen) Dreier Robins, her sister-in-law Ethyl Eyre Valentine Dreier and brother-in-law Raymond Robins provide some insight into the varied social reform and political movements, such as women's suffrage and the Bull Moose Party, with which they were allied. Additionally both Mary and Margaret were active in the Women's Trade Union League, Margaret having served as the League's president from 1907-1922. Therefore their correspondence is a rich resource for scholars interested in women's history and the history of the Progressive Era in the United States.
Due to their shared interest in the arts, her sister Katherine S. Dreier's letters provide information about her own work as an artist, particularly when she was studying abroad, exhibitions in which she participated or visited, and the Cooperative Mural Workshop, a combination art school and workshop that she ran from 1914-1917 with Walt Kuhn, with substantial financial help from Dorothea.
Additionally through her Brooklyn neighborhood, art classes, and support of numerous social causes, Dorothea had a large circle of friends. Frequent correspondents include the Bartlett sisters, Agnes, Mary, and Maud, Rebecca Forbes, Ellen Kuhn Mahan, and Charlotte Schetter. Notable art world correspondents include Vincent van Gogh's sister Elisabeth du Quesne van Gogh, the American Tonalist landscape painter Charles Harold Davis and Dreier's painting instructor and close friend, the painter Walter Shirlaw.
Printed materials reflect the varied interests and activities of Dorothea Dreier and select members of her immediate family through exhibition announcements, catalogs, including a numbered copy of the The Dorothea A. Dreier Exhibition from the memorial exhibition of her work at the Brooklyn Museum of Art in 1925, newspaper clippings relating to her career, the activities of other members of the Dreier family, art and politics; as well as pamphlets, broadsides, brochures and blank postcards.
Photographs include both studio portraits and informal snapshots of Dorothea and Katherine Dreier; group photographs including Dorothea; travel photographs, many of which appear to have been taken in the Netherlands; and photographs of Teddy Roosevelt giving a speech at a railway station. Artworks include a sketchbook by Dreier, five sketchbooks by friend and teacher, Walter Shirlaw, and an unidentified artist, a pencil drawing by Shirlaw, an engraving by Huquier and an etching by Ernest D. Roth.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 5 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1884-1923 (Box 1; 0.75 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1881-1925 (Boxes 1-2; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1883-1916 (Boxes 2-3; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Photographs, circa 1900-1923 (Box 3; 7 folders)
Series 5: Artwork, circa 1885-1941 (Boxes 3-4; 9 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Women's Trade Union League of America; Cooperative Mural Workshop
Subjects-Topical:
Women painters--New York (State)--New York; Women--Suffrage; Suffragists
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Sketchbooks; Pamphlets; Broadsides
Names:
Bartlett, Agnes Willard; Bartlett, Mary F.; Bartlett, Maud W.; Davis, Charles H. (Charles Harold), 1856-1938; Dreier, Katherine Sophie, 1877-1952; Dreier, Mary E. (Mary Elisabeth), 1875-1963; Dreier, Ethyl Eyre Valentine; Forbes, Rebecca; Gogh, Elisabeth du Quesne van, 1859-1936; Kuhn, Walt, 1877-1949; Mahan, Ellen Kuhn; Schetter, Charlotte; Robins, Raymond, 1873-1954; Robins, Margaret Dreier; Shirlaw, Walter, 1838-1909
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1884-1923, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.75 linear feet)
  Items in this series document aspects of the life of Dorothea A. Dreier and include official documents, childhood writings, notes, ephemera, membership cards, invitations, programs, notes, lists, and financial records.
  Official records include Dorothea Dreier's 1912 Passport, insurance policies and a supplemental account to her last will and testament. The folder of invitations, programs and memberships document concerts, recitals, weddings, parties, and exhibitions that Dreier may have attended as well as her membership at the York Club. Scattered amongst the accounts and receipts for household items are receipts for art supplies, frames, and other art-related materials. Other financial records consist of banking records including account passbooks, registers,and cancelled checks.
  Banking records have not been scanned.
  - Passport, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Last Will and Testament - Supplemental Account, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Insurance Policies, 1912-1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Childhood Writings, 1884-1886 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Writing Fragments and Notes, circa 1900-1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lists, before 1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Datebook, 1912 October (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Invitations, Programs and Memberships, circa 1894-1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ephemera, circa 1887-1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Accounts, Bills and Receipts, 1887-1918, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
  - Brooklyn Trust Company Account Passbook, 1917-1918, (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brooklyn Trust Company Check Register, 1916, (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1912, (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1915, (3 folders; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1916, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1917, (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1919, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1920, (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1923, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
- Correspondence, 1881-1925, Series 2:; (Box 1-2; 1.2 linear feet)
  This series contains the correspondence of Dorothea Dreier. Most of the letters are from family and close friends, who addressed her using affectionate nicknames, including "Dodo," "DAD," and "Dadakins." While the letters in this series span from 1881-1925, the majority of them date from 1913-1916, the period during which Drier was at Saranac Lake receiving treatments for her tuberculosis. Business and third-party correspondence, visiting cards, Christmas cards, telegrams, and postcards are also found in this series.
  Due to the number of letters and correspondents this series has been divided into 2 subseries:
  2.1: Family Correspondence, 1881-1923
  2.2: Personal and General Correspondence, 1884-1925
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Family Correspondence, 1881-1923, 2.1
    Family correspondence consists of letters from relatives including members of her immediate family and more distant relatives from Germany. Whenever the relationship of the correspondent to Dorothea is known it has been noted in the folder title. Scattered throughout are letters from Dorothea; most of these were written to her mother (also named Dorothea A. Dreier) and her brother, H. Edward Dreier. Third party correspondence between family members is also found within this subseries.
    There is a large group of letters, postcards, telegrams, and a scrapbook containing additional postcards and letters dated 1887, written by Theodor and his daughters Dorothea and Margaret (Gretchen), to Mrs. Dreier, who appears to have remained behind at the family's Brooklyn home while the other correspondents traveled cross-country to California. Some of the early letters between family members are written in German.
    Dorothea Dreier enjoyed a close and affectionate relationship with her siblings, which is reflected in their correspondence. In addition to recounting quotidian family news and events, letters from her sisters and brother document the public lives of the correspondents. Her sisters Mary E. Dreier and Margret (Gretchen) Dreier Robins discuss their work for the Women's Trade Union League, the women's suffrage movement and the Bull Moose Party. Her brother Edward's letters provide information about family investments and recount the activities of his wife the suffragist, Ethyl Eyre Valentine Dreier. Dorothea was especially close to her youngest sister Katherine due to their shared interest in the arts. Katherine's letters include references to her painting and studies abroad, exhibitions, and the Cooperative Mural Workshop. However, only one letter, dated September 2, 1920, briefly mentions the Société Anonyme.
    This subseries has been scanned in its entirety.
    - Dreier, Anna (cousin), circa 1912-1914 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Dreier, Antoinette (niece), 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Dreier, Dorothea A., 1907-1914 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Dreier, Dorothea A. (mother), 1887-1897, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
    - Dreier, Dorothea A. (mother) - Postcards and Telegrams, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Dreier, Ethyl Eyre Valentine (sister-in-law), 1912-1915 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Dreier, H. Edward (brother), circa 1889-1897, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 35-36)
      (letters received from Dorothea A. Dreier)
    - Dreier, H. Edward (brother), 1908-1915, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
    - Dreier, Katherine S. (sister), 1887, 1908-1923, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
    - Dreier, Ludwig, 1881, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Dreier, Mary E. (sister), 1908-1923, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
    - Dreier, Theodor (father), 1882-1897, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Dreier, Theodor (nephew), 1912-1915 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Knoch, Meta and Elizabeth, 1909-1915 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Robins, Margaret "Gretchen" Dreier (sister), 1907-1915, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 47-48)
    - Robins, Raymond (brother-in-law), 1910-1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Family Members, 1908-1915 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Scrapbook of Family Correspondence1887 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Personal and General Correspondence, 1884-1925, 2.2
    This subseries includes letters from close friends, visiting cards, notes, telegrams, postcards, third party correspondence and business correspondence. Additionally there is a folder of telegrams from Katherine Dreier informing friends and family of Dorothea's death and two folders of condolence letters received by the Dreier family.
    Close friends and regular correspondents include the Bartlett sisters, Agnes, Mary and Maud, Charlotte Schetter, Ellen Kuhn Mahan, Rebecca Forbes, and fellow art student Lillian Miller. Through her travels in the Netherlands and her interest in Vincent van Gogh, Dreier became friends with the artists' sister Elisabeth du Quesne van Gogh and there are six postcards from her in this collection. A 1923 letter from Joseph Stella thanks "Miss Dreier" for purchasing his painting White Heron, but it is impossible to tell if he is referring to Dorothea or Katherine. Julius A. Gross, a local photographer, mentions visiting Dorothea's studio and describes the work found within his letters and includes rough sketches of paintings. He may have been contracted to photograph her work for her during her time at Saranac Lake for a proposed publication.
    Other notable art world correspondents include Charles Harold Davis, the American Tonalist landscape painter, and Walter Shirlaw, a painter who not only was Dreier's teacher, but also a close friend. The Davis letters suggest that Dreier had hoped to study with him, but his letter of 1902 indicates that he would not be teaching that summer and suggests other painting instructors. Other letters discuss paintings that she purchased from the artist. Shirlaw's letters, along with those of his wife Florence, discuss the artist's plans to paint Dorothea's portrait, as well as current exhibitions, works that he has sold, and planned visits to the Dreier sisters, whom he affectionately labeled "the sisterhood." Several of his letters included illustrations.
    Third party correspondence written to Katherine Dreier includes a letter from Walt Kuhn, dated October 14, 1914 that may refer to activities of the Cooperative Mural Workshop. The business correspondence for Dorothea Dreier includes letters related to household purchases, insurance policies, investment accounts and travel reservations. The folder of Katherine Dreier's business correspondence solely is related to work on her home in Stonington, Connecticut.
    - General A-B, 1884-1915 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Abbott, Lyman
      Ackermann, Franzchen
      Alkinson, Winnifred W.
      B., Margaret
      Baldwin, Molly Ives
      Behr, [Minna?]
      Benedict, Z
      Bernuth, Lulu von
      Brackett, Ellen
      Brackett, Mary A.
      Braggiotti, Lilly
      Bristol, Frances
      Bristol, Julia
      Brown, Bertha B.
    - Bartlett, Agnes Willard, 1908-1915 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Bartlett, Mary Fairbanks, 1907-1914 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Bartlett, Maud 1908-1916 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - General C-D, circa 1907-1923 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Chase, William S.
      Chicago No-Jury Society of Artists
      Colton, Margaret W.
      Cullen, Charlotte S.
      Dana, Grace N.
      Davidson, Emily E.
      Dick, Julia
      Dodge, Margaret R.
      Dodge, Susan R.
      Douglas, Maleoliu
      Drew, Emma E.
      Driggs, Alice A.
      Dulman, Cecilia
      Duncan, Frances
      Dutcher, Elizabeth
      Dwyer, M.M.
    - Davis, Charles H. and Frances P., 1902-1910 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - General E-G, 1892-1915 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Elizabeth Duncan School
      Ellsworth, Evelyn P
      Escreet, Jessie M.
      Fairbanks, Henry A.
      Fletcher, Helen B
      Franklin, Stella
      Freiot, Frances
      Fulton, William
      Gozzini, Elisa
    - Edsall, Mrs. David (P.K.), 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Forbes, Rebecca and Reba, 1907-1915 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Foster, Alice H., circa 1914 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Gogh, Elisabeth du Quesne van, circa 1914-1923 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Gross, Julius A., 1912-1915 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - General H-K, 1888-1915 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Hamilton, B. Douglas
      Ye Handicrafts
      Harrington, Helen
      Harris, Margaret
      Healy, [Iannar?]
      Heidlauff, Mary L.
      Higgins, Lothrop D.
      Hills, Laura
      Hoppencled[?], [Anita?]
      Hotzen, Marie
      Hutton, Ada N.
      Ingram, Mary
      Kohlsaat, Käthe
    - Hoppins, Mae, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - General L-N, 1887-1915 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Lascelles, E
      Life and Labor
      Loch, Jacob W.
      Macbeth, William
      Mariotti, Eva
      Marshall, Abby S.
      McKeen, Anna L.
      Meyen, H.A.
      Millspaugh, Mary B
      Moore, Susan
      Moshe, ?
      Mosle, C.
      Müller, Mary L.
      Munnich, Adeline M.
      Murla, Elizabeth W.
      Murren, Marion
      National Women's Trade Union League of America
      Nixon, M
    - Mahan, Ellen Kuhn, 1893-1914 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Miller, Lillian, 1910-1914 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - General O-P, circa 1890-1915 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      O'Brien, Madeleine
      O'Reilly, Leonora
      P., Mary, S.
      Packard, Harriet M.
      Paine, C.M.
      Panerlander, Mariechen
      Pauli, Elizabeth
      Pauli, Hermann
      Pauli, Lillie
      Phelps, ?
      Pitt, Anita
      Plimmer, Gladys
      Plimmer, Hilda
      Portocarrero, Ricardina
      Priestley, Nora D.
      Prudin, Martha L.
      Purón, M.G.
    - Prout, J.S. and Lillian C., circa 1910-1915 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - General Q-R, 1887-1915 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Quinn, Mary
      Rasch, Lilly O.
      Rasmus, Adele M.
      Reinhold, Ferdinand
      Rice, Susie C.
      Robinson, Mary E.
      Rouyon, Adele
      Royce, Elizabeth K.
    - General S, circa 1889-1923 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Saponoff, Lubomir P.
      Schenck, Pendleton
      Schlesinger, Elise
      Schmidt, Alex
      Scott, Melinda
      Seaman, Mary T.
      Sears, E. H.
      Sherman, Julia M.
      Skeel, Emily E. F.
      Smith, M.L.
      Spies, Aelie
      Spitta, Clara
      Stella, Joseph
      Stickney, Katherine H.
      Stone, Winifred
    - Schetter, Charlotte, 1888-1915 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Shirlaw, Florence M., 1903-1914, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-28)
    - Shirlaw, Walter, 1903-1909 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      (includes 3 illustrated letters)
    - General T-W, circa 1900-1915 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Treu, Therese
      Trudeau, E.L.
      V., Nathalie L.
      Ventura, Ludmilla
      Vidaud, N. L.
      W, Lillian D.
      Walker, Edna
      Washburn, ?
      Wendt, Charles W.
      Weyl, Bertha P.
      White, Harriet H.
      White, Lucy S.
      Willigen, van der C.
      Willink, H. M.
      Willis, Florence
      Wise, Zoe L.
      Wiskow, Elizabeth
    - Williston, Mary L., 1910-1915 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Unidentified Correspondents, circa 1887-1923 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Letter Fragments, before 1923 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Third Party Correspondence to Katherine Dreier, 1914-1925 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Visting Cards and Notes, circa 1900-1915 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Christmas Cards, circa 1912-1913 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Telegrams Concerning the Death of Dorothea A. Dreier, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Condolences on the Death of Dorothea A. Dreier, 1923-1924, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 38-39)
    - Business Correspondence, 1897-1916, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
    - Business Correspondence to Katherine S. Dreier, 1908-1910 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Printed Materials, circa 1883-1941, Series 3:; (Boxes 2-3; 0.5 linear feet
  Found in this series are newspaper clippings, exhibition announcements, catalogs, pamphlets, broadsides, maps and blank postcards. Exhibition announcements and catalogs primarily document exhibitions of paintings and drawings by both Dorothea and Katherine Dreier, and include a numbered edition of The Dorothea A. Dreier Exhibition that Katherine Dreier printed privately to commemorate the memorial exhibition at the Brooklyn Museum of Art in 1925.